Finding Aid to the Women's AIDS Network (WAN) Records, 1985-1992
UCSF Library and Center for Knowledge Management, Archives and Special Collections
Women's AIDS Network (WAN) records
1985-1992
MSS 95-04
Women's AIDS Network
Number of containers: 1 carton Linear feet: 1.25
The UCSF Library and Center for Knowledge Management, Archives and Special Collections University of California, San Francisco 530 Parnassus Avenue San Francisco, CA 94143-0840 Phone: (415) 476-8112 Fax: (415) 476-4653 Email: http://www.library.ucsf.edu/collres/archives/contactform.html URL: http://www.library.ucsf.edu/collres/archives/
This collection contains minutes, correspondence, drafts and published articles, bylaws, and other legal documents illustrating the work of the Women's AIDS Network (WAN) from 1986-1992. WAN was the first women's organization among the community service organizations that sprung up around the AIDS crisis.
Information for Researchers
Access
Collection is open for research.
Alternate Forms Available
There are no alternate forms of this collection.
Related Collections
MSS 2000-06 Nancy (Shaw) Stoller Papers
MSS 94-60 San Francisco AIDS Foundation Records
MSS 96-31 Angie Lewis Papers
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
Women's AIDS Network. San Francisco; AIDS (Disease) in women--United States; AIDS (Disease)--Social aspects; AIDS( Disease)--Political aspects; AIDS (Disease)--Patients--Services for; AIDS (Disease)--Law and legislation
Administrative Information
Acquisition Information
The Women's AIDS Network (WAN) Records were donated to the library in 1995.
System of Arrangement
Arranged to the folder level.
Organizational History
The Women's AIDS Network (WAN) was informally established in June of 1983 at the second National AIDS Forum in Denver. In March of 1984, women involved in AIDS services in the Bay Area began meeting as a support group. From this initial support group, WAN evolved into an advocacy organization and informational resource, both for women affected by HIV and for the providers who serve them. WAN provided a forum for information exchange among members who included women in the medical, mental health, and social services fields, along with community activists and social and political advocates and women living with HIV. WAN held regular information sharing meetings for Bay Area members and sent regular informational mailings to members.
WAN sponsored major educational forums and numerous speaking engagements; advocated and organized to support a legislative climate responsive to HIV-affected women's needs; provided informal technical assistance and review to other agencies; distributed information worldwide in response to hundreds of direct requests; developed a model policy on perinatal AIDS antibody testing; sponsored social events; and maintained a resource library and referral service. WAN advocated for public policies, educational materials, and comprehensive services for all HIV-affected women, including women with children, women of all ethnic and economic backgrounds and sexual preferences, women working in the sex industry, and incarcerated women. A special Women's Fund provided small grants to women living with HIV/AIDS in San Francisco. Still, in their own words WAN was "foremost, ... a support network for our members." Members of note include: Sue Williams, treasurer; Eileen Hansen, 1995 Board President; Susyn Almond, 1992 Board President; Angie Lewis (UCSF - Nursing School); Gloria Lockett (CAL-PEP); Ruth Schwartz (AIDS Foundation); Nancy Stoller (UC Santa Cruz); Moher Downing (PHEDRA); Elise Parker (Consortium); Barbara Garcia (CPC Board); and J. D. Bensen (AHP), some of whom are mentioned in the collection.
Scope and Content of Collection
This collection contains minutes, correspondence, bylaws, grant information, project files, and educational files of the San Francisco chapter of the Women's AIDS Network (WAN). WAN started out meeting under the auspices of the San Francisco AIDS Foundation and then reorganized as its own non-profit agency. This collection documents the activities of this organization from its founding in 1984 through 1991, with a few documents from 1992. Additional information on WAN, through 1998, can be found in the Nancy Shaw Stoller Papers (MS 2000-06).
These records document early and continuing advocacy work for women with HIV infection. WAN activities represented in this collection include: development and dissemination of educational materials, consulting, and advising other agencies and non-profits on the needs of HIV positive women, including creating a model policy statement on perinatal AIDS antibody testing.
The first four folders contain bylaws and other structure documents, as well as the "Relationship with San Francisco AIDS Foundation" folder and correspondence. Minutes of the monthly meeting often include flyers for events, articles, and other materials of interest. A membership list is included with the July 1986 minutes, and attendance sheets with names and organizations can be found with many of the later minutes. The October 1986 minutes include an article, "Women and AIDS" by Julie Murphy. A program for the National Council on Family Relations Annual Conference can be found with the September 1987 minutes.
Testimony to the Democratic Party Platform Meeting can be found with both the December 1987 minutes and the "Testimony of WAN Members" folder later in the collection. Other material in that folder includes testimony to the SF Human Rights Commission [and an unidentified piece]. Two more folders document WAN's suggestions to the San Francisco Department of Public Health. WAN's Legislative activities are represented by the Legislative Summary with the February 1988 minutes, as well as the "Legislative and Public Policy" folder with the correspondence.
Financial information includes a folder from the Finance Committee and grant requests. The first folder of RWJ Foundation grant request includes the original Letters of Support; the copies that were attached to the actual application are found in the second folder. WAN's own small grant program, the Special Women's Fund, is represented by a single page describing the project. The articles and information files consist primarily of copies of journal and magazine articles, but some files also include original information. There are also a few folders of information on other WAN chapters/WAN activities in other cities and other related Women's and AIDS organizations. These organizations include Perinatal HIV Reduction and Education Demonstration Activity (PHREDA), a project associated with WAN member Moher Downing, flyers for Project AWARE, and educational materials from the Women's Action Alliance.
Container List
- "Strategizing and Structure" - founding and review of purpose documents, 1984-1988; 1990 (Carton 1, Folder 1)
- Structure Committee, 1988; undated (Carton 1, Folder 2)
- Goals Brainstorming, 1988 (Carton 1, Folder 3)
- By-laws, 1988; 1991 (Carton 1, Folder 4)
- Membership Meeting Minutes (Carton 1, Folder 5-47)
  - September, October, December 1984 (Carton 1, Folder 5)
  - February - October, December 1985 (Carton 1, Folder 6)
  - January 1986 (Carton 1, Folder 7)
  - February - March, May - September 1986 (Carton 1, Folder 8)
  - October 1986 (Carton 1, Folder 9)
  - November 1986 (Carton 1, Folder 10)
  - December 1986 (Carton 1, Folder 11)
  - January 1987 (Carton 1, Folder 12)
  - February 1987 (Carton 1, Folder 13)
  - March 1987 (Carton 1, Folder 14)
  - April 1987 (Carton 1, Folder 15)
  - May 1987 (Carton 1, Folder 16)
  - June 1987 (Carton 1, Folder 17)
  - July 1987 (Carton 1, Folder 18)
  - August 1987 (Carton 1, Folder 19)
  - September 1987 (Carton 1, Folder 20)
  - October 1987 (Carton 1, Folder 21)
  - November 1987 (Carton 1, Folder 22)
  - December 1987 (Carton 1, Folder 23)
  - January 1988 (Carton 1, Folder 24)
  - February 1988 (Carton 1, Folder 25)
  - March 1988 (Carton 1, Folder 26)
  - April 1988 (Carton 1, Folder 27)
  - May 1988 (Carton 1, Folder 28)
  - June 1988 (Carton 1, Folder 29)
  - July 1988 (Carton 1, Folder 30)
  - August 1988 (Carton 1, Folder 31)
  - September 1988 (Carton 1, Folder 32)
  - October 1988 (Carton 1, Folder 33)
  - November 1988 (Carton 1, Folder 34)
  - December 1988 (Carton 1, Folder 35)
  - January 1989 (Carton 1, Folder 36)
  - February 1989 (Carton 1, Folder 37)
  - March 1989 (Carton 1, Folder 38)
  - April 1989 (Carton 1, Folder 39)
  - May 1989 (Carton 1, Folder 40)
  - June 1989 (Carton 1, Folder 41)
  - August 1989 (Carton 1, Folder 42)
  - September - October 1989 (Carton 1, Folder 43)
  - November - December 1989 (Carton 1, Folder 44)
  - January - March, May - December 1990 (Carton 1, Folder 45)
  - January - December 1991 (Carton 1, Folder 46)
  - January - December 1992 (Carton 1, Folder 47)
- Board Meeting Minutes, February - April 1992 (Carton 1, Folder 48)
- Membership Retreats, 1988-1991 (Carton 1, Folder 49)
- Board Nominations, 1986-1988 (Carton 1, Folder 50)
- Board Election - Final Ballots, 1988 (Carton 1, Folder 51)
- Board Resignations, 1990 (Carton 1, Folder 52)
- Meeting Time Survey, January, 1988 (Carton 1, Folder 53)
- Correspondence (Carton 1, Folder 54-58)
  - Official, 1986-1990; undated (Carton 1, Folder 54)
  - Internal, 1987; 1990 (Carton 1, Folder 55)
  - Relationship with San Francisco AIDS Foundation (SFAF), 1987 (Carton 1, Folder 56)
  - Cross-Cultural Training - Polaris Research and Development, 1988 (Carton 1, Folder 57)
  - Legislative and Public Policy Correspondence, 1988 (Carton 1, Folder 58)
- Descriptive Literature, 1991; undated (Carton 1, Folder 59)
- Policy Statement - Perinatal HIV Antibody Testing, 1988 (Carton 1, Folder 60)
- Testimony of WAN Members, 1986-1987 (Carton 1, Folder 61)
- Input to San Francisco Department of Public Health (SFDPH) Reports, 1986; 1987 (Carton 1, Folder 62)
- SFDPH - Five Year Plan Questionnaire, 1987 (Carton 1, Folder 63)
- Finance Committee, 1989 (Carton 1, Folder 64)
- Special Women's Fund, 1992 (Carton 1, Folder 65)
- State Contract Bids, 1987 (Carton 1, Folder 66)
- Grant Requests (Carton 1, Folder 67-69)
  - Junior League, 1987 (Carton 1, Folder 67)
  - Robert Wood Johnson Foundation (2 folders), 1988 (Carton 1, Folder 68-69)
- Administrative Assistant Job Description, 1989 (Carton 1, Folder 70)
- Resources for HIV Positive Women, undated (Carton 1, Folder 71)
- Women and HIV Resource Materials Packets (Carton 1, Folder 72-73)
  - Folder 1, circa 1990 (Carton 1, Folder 72)
  - Folder 2, 1987 (Carton 1, Folder 73)
- World AIDS Day, 1990 (Carton 1, Folder 74)
- Photographic Shows and Cleis Press Call for Submissions, 1987 (Carton 1, Folder 75)
- Articles/Information Files (Carton 1, Folder 76-87)
  - Breastfeeding - What are the Choices, 1987 (Carton 1, Folder 76)
  - Childcare Issues and AIDS, 1987 (Carton 1, Folder 77)
  - AIDS in Children (technical), 1986 (Carton 1, Folder 78)
  - Perinatal Transmission - Mother & Infant, 1987 (Carton 1, Folder 79)
  - Pregnancy and AIDS (Question and Answer), 1987 (Carton 1, Folder 80)
  - Prostitutes and AIDS, 1987 (Carton 1, Folder 81)
  - AIDS and Lesbians, 1986-1991 (Carton 1, Folder 82)
  - Impact of AIDS on Women, 1986-1987 (Carton 1, Folder 83)
  - AIDS and Women at Risk, 1987-1991 (Carton 1, Folder 84)
  - Women and AIDS Books, 1988; 1990 (Carton 1, Folder 85)
  - Health Care Workers and Their Patients, 1986 (Carton 1, Folder 86)
  - Family Planning Clinics and AIDS, 1986 (Carton 1, Folder 87)
- Other WAN chapters/activities (Carton 1, Folder 88-90)
  - Sacramento, California, 1986; undated (Carton 1, Folder 88)
  - Seattle, Washington (Health Information Network), 1988 (Carton 1, Folder 89)
  - New York and New Jersey, 1987 (Carton 1, Folder 90)
- Other Organizations (Carton 1, Folder 91-93)
  - PHREDA (Perinatal HIV Reduction and Education Demonstration Activity), undated (Carton 1, Folder 91)
  - Project AWARE (Association for Women's AIDS Research and Education), UCSF at San Francisco General, 1989; undated (Carton 1, Folder 92)
  - Women's Action Alliance - Educational Materials (Catalog), 1988 (Carton 1, Folder 93)